So in the last lecture, we finished our rule setup with adding a rule for images,
Yani son derste, kural kural grntlere bir kural ekleyerek bitirdik, imdi
now I want to have a look at plugins and then see if the setup actually works.
eklentilere bakmak istiyorum ve kurulumun gerekten ie yarayp yaramadn grmek istiyorum.
Now regarding plugins, it's actually super simple for us here,
imdi eklentilerle ilgili olarak, aslnda burada bizim iin sper basit, gelitirme i
we don't need any for development workflow,
ak iin herhangi bir ihtiyacmz
we will add one later when we set this up for production, there
yok, bunu retim iin ayarladmzda bir tane daha ekleyeceiz, orada bir
I want to add some plugin
eklenti eklemek istiyorum
but for now that is all, I won't add a plugin here.
ama imdilik hepsi iin, buraya bir eklenti eklemez.
So with that we can have a look at the setup we used here and see if we save the file, if this works
Bylece, burada kullandmz kuruluma bir gz atabilir ve dosyay kaydedip kaydetmediimizi grebiliriz, eer bu
if we run our start script which runs the dev server which I said would automatically take this config
betik dosyasn altracam dev sunucusunu altran balang betiimizi altrrsak bu ie
file.
yarar.
So let's run this script with npm start, make sure all files are saved
Yani bu betii npm start ile altralm, tm dosyalarn kaydedildiinden emin
and let's see if this works, we get an error here that the path is not an absolute path,
olun ve bunun ie yarayp yaramadna bakalm, burada yolun mutlak bir yol olmadn bir hatayla karlatk, bu
so something with our output path is wrong.
yzden kt yolumuzla ilgili bir ey yanltr.
Let's have a look at it, let's go to our webpack
una bir bakalm, webpack yaplandrmasna
config, path here for output,
gidelim, kt iin buradan yola kalm, ben
well I messed that up, didn't I?
de onu kartrdm, deil mi?
Path should be this part here and public path should be the empty string,
Yol burada bu ksm olmal ve bo yol dize olmal, bu dzeltme ile
so with this fix let's now try it again,
imdi tekrar deneyelim, ayrca gncellenmi config
also make sure to save the updated config file.
dosyasn da kaydettiinizden emin olun.
So now at least it doesn't crash when starting the server,
imdi en azndan sunucu balatlrken kmez,
it does give us an error though that it doesn't understand this import syntax here, the
bize bu ithalat szdizimini anlamad halde, dinamik ie aktarm szdizimini
dynamic import syntax, it doesn't understand this.
anlamamza ramen bir hata veriyor, bunu anlamyor.
So how do we make it to understand this dynamic import? We need to adjust our setup here to be able to
Peki bu dinamik ithalat anlamaya nasl yardmc oluruz? Dinamik olarak oluturulmu fazladan kod paralar oluturabilmek iin buradaki
create dynamically generated extra chunks of code,
kurulumumuzu ayarlamamz gerekiyor. Tembel ykleme, balangta indirilen ana
lazy loading means that it's an extra bundle and not part of the main bundle which is downloaded initially,
paketin bir paras deil, web paketindeki kod blnmesini desteklemek ve kod blme
to support code splitting in webpack and code splitting is just a different name for lazy loading,
yapmak iin ekstra bir paket anlamna geliyor. tembel ykleme iin farkl bir ad,
I have to add chunkFileName here to my output config.
chunkFileName'i k yaplandrmam iin buraya eklemeliyim.
This simply determines what these other files, the separate files which are generated for the lazy loaded
Bu sadece, bu dier dosyalarn ne olduunu, elbette pakette yer almayan tembel yklenen kod iin retilen, kod
code which is of course not included in the bundle,
blme ileminin amacn ortadan kaldran, bu
that would defeat the purpose of code splitting,
dosya adnn ne olmas gerektiini
what these file name should be named.
belirleyen ayr dosyalar belirler.
They have to have a variable part in their name because they are generated by webpack dynamically,
Webpack tarafndan dinamik olarak retildikleri iin adlarnda deiken bir para olmas gerekiyor, ben
I'll use ID.js
ID kullanacam. js burada,
here, IDs are dynamically generated ID 0, 1, 2 and so on, generated by webpack
ID'ler dinamik olarak oluturulmu ID 0, 1, 2 ve benzeri, web paketi tarafndan oluturulmutur, bylece
so that feature is outsourced into separate bundles received their own javascript files.
zellik ayr demetler halinde d kaynakl olarak kendi javascript dosyalarn almtr.
Additionally we need to make babel aware of this dynamic import syntax which it otherwise doesn't understand,
Ek olarak, bu anlama gelmedii bu dinamik ie aktarm szdizimini babelden haberdar
so what I'll do is I'll install a plugin, npm install --save-dev,
etmemiz gerekiyor, bu yzden yapacam ey bir eklenti ykleyeceim,
it's called babel-plugin-syntax dynamic import and this will make sure that babel understands
npm install --save-dev, buna babel-plugin-syntax dynamic deniliyor Ithalat ve bu babel bu dinamik ithalat szdizimini
this dynamic import syntax.
anladndan emin olacaktr.
So once this was installed, we can go to the babelrc file and we already get presets, now I'll also add a
Bu yzden bir kez kurulduktan sonra, babelrc dosyasna gidebiliriz ve zaten nayarlar alyoruz, imdi
plugins node here which also is an array
de bir dizi olan bir eklenti dm de ekleyeceim
and here I'll add my syntax dynamic import plugin,
ve burada benim szdizimi dinamik ie aktarma eklentisini ekleyeceim,
so that's the name of the plugin.
yani bu isim eklentinin
With that added, let's save all these files and let's retry npm start and see if this now works,
Buna ek olarak, tm bu dosyalar saklayalm ve npm'i yeniden balatalm ve imdi alp almadna bakalm, imdi bu
now this compiles but we get a different error,
derler ama farkl bir hata alrz, bu
we get an error that this syntax here where we assign our properties like this isn't liked.
szdizimini burada bizim mlklerimizi tahsis ettiimiz yer bu gibi deil diye bir hata alrz .
The reason for this is that the env preset which we're using, this one here only supports latest browser
Bunun nedeni, kullanmakta olduumuz env n ayarnn, buradaki zelliin yalnzca bir paras olan en yeni
features that are part of the specification,
tarayc zelliklerini desteklediidir. Bu zel zellik
this special property syntax is only in draft state though and it's not included in the env preset,
szdizimi yalnzca taslak halindedir ve env n ayarnda yer almaz. Sorun deil, sadece
isn't a problem though we just have to add another preset.
baka bir n ayar eklememiz gerek.
So with npm install save-dev, we now install another preset which is named babel-preset-stage-2,
imdi, npm install save-dev ile, imdi babel-preset-stage-2, stage 2 n ayarlar olarak adlandrlan baka
stage 2 presets simply are draft features which may eventually get supported but which we
bir n ayar yklyoruz, en sonunda desteklenebilecek ama zaten kullanmak
already want to use.
istediimiz taslak zellikler.
So with that we have to add this to our setup here and I'll add my preset in the middle, I'll add stage-2
Bylece bunun kurulumunu buraya ekledik ve n ayarm ortada ekleyeceim, ben de bu
here, like this.
aamada 2. aama ekleyeceim.
Let's now try this again with npm start and now this looks better,
imdi npm start ile bunu tekrar deneyelim ve imdi bu daha
at least we don't get an error,
iyi grnyor, en azndan bir hata
we'll face one problem though.
alamyoruz, yine de bir problemle karlaacaz.
The application is now served and by default, it's doing that on localhost8080, so let's open that,
Uygulama imdi ve varsaylan olarak, localhost8080 zerinde yapyor, bu yzden aalm, orada uygulamay grmeyiz,
there however we won't see app,
nedeni u ki, bu ekilde
the reason is that we didn't connect our build output which by the way is not stored in the dist folder
ina edilen kmz birbirine balamadk. Webpack dev-server' kullandmzda, ancak bu bellekte, indeksle bu
when we use webpack dev-server but in memory, that we didn't connect that output with the index.html
k balamadmz zaman dist klasr. html dosyas, bu dosyada
file,
hibir
we have no imports in that file,
ithalatmz yok, bu
how would we add the script to it?
betii nasl ekleyelim?
That is something we have to do on our own and we will do that in the next lecture.
Bu bizim kendi bamza yapmamz gereken bir ey ve bunu bir sonraki derste yapacaz.